Ahmad Ali

Technology Enthusiast, FullStack, Javascript Engineer

<u>Github Profile</u> Repositories49 Stars1.9K Followers43

<u>Stackoverflow Profile</u> Reputation 4.5K+ Badges80+ Answers45+

I am a 27 year old full stack developer and team lead, currently working at Intech, Lahore. I love everything that has to do with the latest developments in software and especially in JS world. I have experience in design & architecture of micro-frontends with microservices, backed with Node, Python, .Net and cloud platforms like Firebase & cloud functions. I feel a true devotion to open source world and contribute actively.

I write on software development occasionally on Quora & Medium. I'd love to work with people, having passion and interest in the latest technologies, frameworks and products which have direct impact on our world.

EXPERIENCE

Intech Process Automation, Lahore — Lead Developer, Technical Product Owner

June 2019 - Present

Part of the product suit being developed at Intech, Self service AI is a data-driven machine learning or model training app to be used directly by customers and other companion products like CMS and operations performance monitoring for model training and scoring.

I am working as the technical product owner to get requirements, create user stories, run sprints, and work as a lead developer for connecting different microservices of a base platform, and designing architecture for major parts of the app on frontend as well on backend.

Technologies being used are ReactJS,, Node.js, Prisma, GraphQL, Apollo Client, GraphDB, ScriptingEngine (Python), Postgres DB, Micro-frontends, Keycloak, Flask, Python, gRPC, Typescript, dockers.

Intech Process Automation, Lahore — Senior Front End Developer

June 2017 - May 2019

Teamplay marries big data systems and microservices with machine learning and industrial standards to enable Industry 4.0 applications and can run on bare metal as well as the cloud.

I worked as senior frontend developer, responsible for the visual parts, frontend app in React backed with flask app (Python). Maintenance and monitoring of the micro-services related to frontend app.

Technology stack comprises MQTT, Flink, TimescaleDB, Docker, DCOS, Ansible, Postgres, Flask, React, Redux, Avro SerDe/RPC, Zeppelin, OpenRDF, Redis, Spark, and Keycloak and languages Python, Golang, and Javascript. Data science with



Park Avenue, F-11, Islamabad **Mobile:** +923446843940

Email: ahmadalibaloch@gmail.com

Development SKILLS

- Architecturing SPAs.
 Micro-frontends,
 Reactive/Functional
 Programming, building JS
 libraries, standalone react
 components and contributing in
 open source frameworks.
- Typescript, ES6,ES5, RxJs,
 Node.js, ReactJs, AngularJs 1-2,
 Vue.Js, Breeze.js, NPM/Gulp
 tooling, Yarn, WebPack latest.
- Google Material design for Angular and its variations for bootstrap and Vue.js
- Realtime Applications using Firebase live database, Realm on Android and Web.
- WebAPIs development on Asp.Net, Breeze.js, GraphQL and consuming on Web+Android.
- Backed: Azure Cloud, Google Cloud Apps, Asp.Net, Core, backend development with Entity Framework.
- Project Management:
 Slack, Jira, Bitbucket, Visual
 Studio Online

Pandas, Numpy, Spark ML Pipelines, and Tensorflow as the underlying technology fabric. Baked in agile methods, test driven development, and CI/CD into the engineering process from day 1.

DG Heating, UK — *Mobile & FrontEnd Engineer*

March 2015 - July 2017

DG Heating provides full heating solutions from measuring house building details, availing government deals and finally installing boilers and related equipment.

I Joined the startup as full stack developer and took part in architecturing & development of the company admin app and website in C# on Azure Cloud, WebApis, AngularJs, plus a native Android App for on the ground surveyors to accomplish their jobs, connect in real time written in Kotlin.

AmalJamaee, UAE — Senior Front End Developer

July 2014 - Jan 2015

The company developed a productivity app for enterprises to monitor, enhance and accomplish company goals.

I Joined remotely as a FrontEnd developer in a complete team of 10-15 people. Test driven development of Organization BreakThroughs (ORGBT) with Agile/Scrum methodology in an international team. Project details below.

Expertflow, Switzerland — *Software Engineer*

June 2013 - Feb 2015

Expertflow is an international company, headquartered in Switzerland and working in Pakistan, Egypt, Morocco and Kenya. The company provides solutions for Cisco contact centers (UCCE, UCCX or PCCE).

I joined in Pakistan office, as a software engineer to work on Bidstruct a multi-tenant web App - which shortens the presales process from days to minutes, reduces risks and improves offer qualities.

PROJECTS

DG Heating Web App & Website — Witline Team

This app is a complete all in one solution for all company tasks including a custom Angular CMS to build/change front end website in minutes. Web app has an intelligent jobflow which automatically progresses assigning jobs to proper employees in real time, ending in generation of quotation. Admins control the jobflow, catalog and company calendars. Customers follow a suggestions based combinations (A.I) wizard to generate quotations for them. We have internal custom libraries and extensively rely on open source libraries.

Contribution in:

- Backend Application architecture with C# codeFirst database design using Entity Framework,
- Odata WebAPIs and Breeze WebAPIs

Learnings & Fun Projects

Side Projects in this time

Android/Web app to explore/track goals make in elections by different parties. <u>Trump Meter App</u>, Khan Meter App

Angular 2 app to explore and watch categorized videos content. <u>Video</u> lectures

Launching a companion Android App in material design, live Firebase and Realm database offline with ads on Google Play Store. Learning to create Google Adwords campaigns and Adsense account usage and creating ads design in Adobe.

Learning IoT and electronics with Google Android Things. Learning big data concepts and applying on the Wizard in DG Heating App.

Expertflow/Amaljamaee Job Side Projects

Creating an Open Source JS library Angular Multi-range and publishing on Bower hosting. You can have many sliders with different color slides from a simple JS model.

- LiveChat & Custom Opt-in Notifications using Firebase,
- AngularJS app from scratch, Material Design layouts, custom web components with Angularjs 1/2,
- Custom AngularJs Drag-Drop CMS for front-end website compiled on server
- Combinations based A.I. wizard design and development
- Development of the 2D-3D house design app with a remote 3D js developer (paperjs and threejs)

DG Heating Android App — Witline Team

App is connected with real time database and Azure APIs where surveyors update information, upload pictures, chat, and comment about assigned jobs and projects from customers locations. The app is offline first and ressources friendly to efficiently complete tasks. Admins can login to control job flow.

- Android Clean Architecture using Square. Inc and standard open source libraries
- Google Material Design components for Android
- Realm and Firebase live database
- Background services to efficiently manage sync and upload
- Login and Auth services

Organizations Breakthrough — Amaljamaee Remote Team

A commercial product that is aimed to transform organizations by taking strategic planning to whole new levels. Simplifying the ability of the organization for building strategic plans, follow up the plans, and steering on their plans if issues are found.

Contributions in:

- Database design to Web API and their consumption,
- AngularJS custom components,
- Material Design theme implementation in existing app,
- Dashboard with visual cards and charts.

Bidstruct — Experflow Lahore Team

Development of the Bidstruct, a Web App using AngularJS and latest tools and frameworks with Microsoft .Net Odata / Web API Restful services.

Bidstruct shortens the pre-sales process from days to minutes, reduces risks and improves offer quality

Contributions in:

- New Angular Project Architecture based on APIs and Angular Js 1
 SPA from old Asp.Net project
- Development and Database Design for Extensible and Multi-tenant app.
- Web API / Odata APIs, Authorization service, permissions and user management.

School & University Life

Written the famous most voted 20K+, answer on Quora about what are the best study methods. Topping google results too.

Creating a simple FM Transmitter applying learnings of electronics in matric School.

Visual Prayer Times SPA

Displaying Day & Night timing of prayers visually internationally based on Time Zone and Equation of Time. Drawn in a colorful round clock design on HTML Canvas. Raw JS, no libraries.

Shopping Hub

A PHP Project with custom MVC framework, Product searching from catalog with vendors authorization in a nice simple design

AWARDS

Talent Award 2009 Chief Minister Punjab,

Full scholarship for undergraduate studies.

Winner of **PEEF Punjab** Pakistan scholarship monthly

Position Holder in Intermediate with distinction from relevant board of education (Sargodha).

LANGUAGES

English, Urdu, Basic Arabic

• Real-time notifications using SignalR and training other members on new technology.

EDUCATION

University of Bradford, UK — BEng. Software Engineering

Sept 2009 - June 2013

Awarded full scholarship for undergraduate studies. Passed the program with honours degree and Dean's Award. Winner of PEEF Pakistan scholarship.

Degree College, Mianwali — *I.C.S*, *Intermediate*

May 2007 - July 2009

Position Holder in Intermediate with distinction from relevant board of education (Sargodha).